<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle to Friends concerning the present and succeeding times being a faithful exhortation and warning to all Friends who profess the truth to beware of the manifold wiles of the enemy and to stand armed in the light of the Lord God of heaven and earth against his assaults, that so they may be ready to answer the call and requirings of the Lord : also, some thing signified of the mistery of the succeeding times, that all may be prepared and that the evil day may not overtake any at unawares, but such as turn away their ear from counsel / by Stephen Crisp.</title>
            <author>Crisp, Stephen, 1628-1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80816</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202128</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09523150</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09523150</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135339</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80816)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135339)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1328:30 or 2529:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle to Friends concerning the present and succeeding times being a faithful exhortation and warning to all Friends who profess the truth to beware of the manifold wiles of the enemy and to stand armed in the light of the Lord God of heaven and earth against his assaults, that so they may be ready to answer the call and requirings of the Lord : also, some thing signified of the mistery of the succeeding times, that all may be prepared and that the evil day may not overtake any at unawares, but such as turn away their ear from counsel / by Stephen Crisp.</title>
                  <author>Crisp, Stephen, 1628-1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Include errata.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library; Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135339:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN Epiſtle to Friends, Concerning the PRESENT and SUCCEEDING TIMES. BEING A faithful Exhortation and Warning to all Friends, who profeſs the Truth, to be ware of the manifold Wiles of the Enemy, and to ſtand Armed in the Light of the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, againſt his Aſſaults, that ſo they may be ready to anſwer the Call and Requirings of the Lord. ALSO, Some thing ſignified of the Miſery of the Succeeding Times, that all may be prepared, and that the Evil Day may not overtake any at unawares, but ſuch as turn away their Ear from Counſel.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Let him that hath an Ear, hear what the Spirit ſaith to the Churches.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>By one who is a Traveller in the Way of Peace and hath good will to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all Men, and more eſpecially to the Houſhold of Faith. <hi>STEPHEN CRISP.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1666.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:135339:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:135339:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN Epiſtle to Friends, Concerning the PRESENT and SUCCEEDING TIMES.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU whom the Lord hath reached unto in this the day of his Love, and hath made known the way of Truth and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs unto you, through the raiſing up of that holy, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Witneſs of himſelf, that long lay hid and buried in you, and hath brought you to a ſecret feeling of ſomething in you, that is worth the minding and regarding; and the Lord cauſing this to appear in the day of your ſeeking, as a Light, diſcovering Darkneſs, and its power, by which ye were formerly holden, and giving you, by his Spirit, a ſenſe and ſecret hope, that in this Light, the way of Deliverance was to obtained unto; this hope made you not aſhamed of the Light which before you hated, but you came to own &amp; embrace it, even while others ſtill hated it and you, for its ſake; yet your hearts being affected with the hope that did appear therein, could not but ſo far joyn unto it, as to make publick profeſſion of it for its own ſake; and for no other ends or deſignes, or intereſt at all, but with reſolution in that Light, to wait for the Salvation of God. Dear Friends, it is you afore-mentioned that both now, and for ſome days and weeks, my heart hath been deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſed concerning, even night and day; and the aboundings of the Fathers love doth often overcome me, and draws me forth now to ſay and write theſe things unto you for your admonition &amp; eſtabliſhment; and indeed it is you who did thus rightly own the way of Truth, and knew your believing to be the gift and mercy of God to your ſouls, that I do aim at; for thoſe that have taken up the profeſſion of the precious Truth upon by reſpects and ſiniſter ends, and but for reaſons propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135339:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>in their carnal minds; though I do pitty them, yet I have not much at this time to ſay to them, but this; <hi>The day ſhall declare them, and their garment ſhall not hide them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you, oh my friends, who had fellowſhip with us, in the deep travels of our beginnings, and did come to Truth the ſame way, and have known the power and virtue of it, many times overcoming you in your inward man, which hath made you cry out, <hi>Lord evermore give us of this Bread;</hi> and hath made you as a watred Garden: Oh Friends, how ſhall I expreſs or ſignify unto you thoſe long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, thoſe ardent deſires and earneſt breathings of my ſoul, that you, even you, might abide to the end of all tryals, and tribulation, and adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities; and might inherit that Crown of Immortality, that is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, and might not by any meanes be bereft thereof; this is ſingly my travel in Body and Spirit, that you might be kept and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved out of all the ſubtile ſnares of the wicked one, which hunts for the ſoul, even of thoſe that have believed; and therefore in dear and tender love I have a few things to write unto you for the clearing of my Conſcience, and diſcharging my duty in the ſight of the Lord, and the Lord give you all a tender and an underſtanding heart, that both you and I may yet have cauſe daily to praiſe the Lord in the glorious Light of his Salvation, which he hath manifeſted amongſt us, by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing his Son Chriſt Jeſus, to whom belongs <hi>Dominion, Honour and Glory for ever, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt, dear Friends, it is in my heart to put you in remenbrance of that by which we were called and convinced, which as a foundation Principle was laid in and among you, and it being unchangable and unalterable in it ſelf, doth therefore admit of no alteration or change in thoſe that are rightly kept to it.</p>
            <p>It was a Light which aroſe in our hearts, and ſhined forth from God, the Father of Lights, carrying in its appearance the nature and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of God, both in its condemning evil, which the Enemy had ſown or planted in us; and owning, allowing, and juſtifying every thing that was good and honeſt, juſt and equal; even thoſe thoughts in our hearts which were of turning towards the Lord, and ſeeking his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; theſe thoughts were juſtified and encouraged by the Light, and all the contrary diſcovered and judged, as they were brought to it to be tried. Now this Light did our ſouls rejoyce in, as they had good cauſe, though it took away our former rejoycings; our pleaſures in vanities and iniquity died, our glory in this world withered, our friendſhip with the Sons of men decayed, and we ſtood in the Light, and ſaw all theſe things, and were not ſorry at it, but waited daily to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135339:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſee theſe things more and more brought to paſs, neither was there a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting our thoughts to go out, how we might prevent thoſe damages, or repair theſe loſſes, but the Croſs of Chriſt was indeed our glorying or rejoycing; and the hope that was before us, did make us deſpiſe the pleaſure, treaſures and honours, friendſhip and delights of this world; and in thoſe dayes you grew into a feeling of the heavenly joy, where the hundred-fold was witneſſed in your boſoms, and the zeal of the Lord was kindled by his own Spirit in you, againſt whatſoever this Light of Jeſus in the Conſcience did witneſs againſt; and the Lord beheld your integrity, and bleſſed you, and multiplied you, and added to your ſtrength and ſtature, and then did the fruits of this glorious work abound among you, in three more general and ſpecial effects, by which effects, or by their continuance among you, let all now come to ſearch and try themſelves, that ſo, dear Friends, thoſe that have conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued faithful in them all, may perſevere in like manner to the end: and thoſe, who upon true ſearch do find, that they have failed, and fallen ſhort in all or any of them, may make haſt to repent, and to turn to that which was the root of them all, that they may not be found, as fruitleſs and withered branches, in the day that cometh, leſt they be cut off and utterly conſumed and blotted out from among the living bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Vine; for a day cometh that Truth will look into the Fig-Tree for Fruit, and Leaves will not defend it from the Curſe and Blaſting.</p>
            <p>The three eſpecial fruits that did ſpring forth from this bleſſed root, and were and are to continue, and increaſe in us, and amongſt us to the end, are theſe;</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Purity,</hi> manifeſted in a godly Converſation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> manifeſted in dear and tender Love one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Faithfulneſs,</hi> manifeſted in bearing a conſtant and faithful Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the things we had received and believed, though it were unto great loſs and ſufferings.</p>
            <p>And againſt all theſe do the wicked one appear to ſee if he can make you barren concerning them, and that with divers wiles and ſubtilties, that he may prevail on you, and not be known to be the Enemy, but might ſo overcome you, as that you might both ſubmit to him, and then plead for him and his ſnares and wiles, as being juſt, right, lawful, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, convenient, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But, oh dear Friends, let all be watchful and diligent to wait in the ſence and true feeling of that Seed that never fell nor was beguiled; and you will (even the leaſt of you) ſee and comprehend his workings and transformings, and be delivered from them.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:135339:4"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Purity</hi> and <hi>Holineſs</hi> was a fruit in you which doth yet flouriſh in many <hi>(bleſſed be the Lord)</hi> who are as watchful and careful to approve themſelves in obedience to the Light of Truth in their inward parts as ever; &amp; finds as great a neceſſity both of trying &amp; judging with its judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as ever; theſe having thus waited, have renewed their ſtrength unto this very day, and do mount up as upon the wings of the Eagle; theſe are neither weary in running, nor faint they in their walking; But alas, Friends, even theſe do know with how great and manifold aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faults they have been aſſaulted, and know and ſee with ſorrow of heart how the aſſault hath prevailed upon ſome, by working into the mind a ſecret Liberty, and ſuppoſed enlargedneſs, whereby a careleſneſs hath entered ſome, and they having no keeper, but the meaſure of Light re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in their hearts and conſciences, ſo ſoon as they came to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to ſlight the reproofs of that, they ſoon erred; and this ſuppoſed Liberty entered, that now after ſo many years ſtrictneſs and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, they ſhould not need now to ſtand ſo ſtraitly to try things and words as at firſt, becauſe now, a day of more Liberty was come, and this Liberty ſecretly prevailed againſt that pure fear that once was pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in their hearts, and againſt the very obedience of Truth, inwardly in the ſubjection of the mind, and then it became manifeſt outwardly; the actions ſometimes blame-worthy, the words and ſpeech again cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and run into the old channel of the World, like them again, and the ſingle pure Language, learned in the Light, in the time of their poverty and ſimplicity, almoſt loſt and forgotten, and ſo the work of God which he wrought, in a manner laid waſte; and then, when this Liberty is entred, and made uſe of as aforeſaid, oftentimes a ſecret ſubtilty ariſeth againſt the judgment of Truth, either from within, or from any outwardly, that are grieved with this looſe and careleſs kind of ſpeaking or acting, which ſubtilly leads to contend for it, or againſt the judgment, telling the Creature, why theſe things are but ſmall things, and little things, and what, we muſt not ſtrain at a Gnat, and ſuch like. Oh my Friends, beware of theſe evil ſuggeſtions of the wicked One; how came they to be ſmall and little things, ſeeing they were great things with us in the beginning? and how comes an offence of this nature to be light now, ſeeing it was heavy in the beginning? Oh let not the greateſt Mercies of our God ſo fill us, as to make us ſlight or forget the leaſt obedience; but rather let the continuance of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy the more quicken you up unto a zeal for his Name and Truth in all things, to be found doing and ſpeaking according to the Rule of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, which ye learned in the Light, in the day of your being low and little, and then nothing will riſe up and be exalted in the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135339:4"/>of Gods mercies, but that holy birth which lives in purity when it is at higheſt; and ſo that life of Righteouſneſs will ſhine forth more and more, which glorifies God and ſeeks his honour. Dear Friends, that ye might be ſo kept unto the end is the breathing and travel of my ſoul: and that where this neglect hath entred, and this aforeſaid cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption either in ſpeech or action is to be found, that ye would receive the Word of Exhortation in meekneſs and fear, in which it is written unto you, and may redeem the time, for the dayes are and will be evil; and none will hold the myſtery of the Faith (that ſaves from falling in the evil day) but ſuch as do keep the pure and undefiled Conſcience, which none can do but by perſiſting and continuing in the daily ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Spirit, and belief and obedience of the the Truth.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Fruit that was brought forth from this good Root, was <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> one towards another; which, bleſſed be the Lord, is preciouſly preſerved in and among many to this very day; who are ſo ſenſible of the divers operations of Truth in them, to be all by one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that they are ſtill kept of one heart and mind, given up freely to ſerve the Lord in ſinglneſs of heart in their generation; and are in this good work as ſtrengtheners and encouragers of one another; but not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the enemy hath been exceeding buſie to lay waſte and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy this bleſſed effect alſo, and that under divers pretences, which the Lord ſtill diſcovered by his own Light and Spirit in his People, who have ſingly waited upon him; but many have been his wiles, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times fitting and preparing veſſels to riſe up in the fleſhly and ſenſual wiſdom; &amp; to traduce &amp; bring in corrupt and evil doctrines, to try who was not ſound in the Faith, that they may draw them aſide into a heat and zeal for ſomething which had not its root in the Truth, and which they that abode in the Truth could not own, but judge and condemn in the Name of the Lord; which when ſuch ſaw, they took thereat oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of ſtriving to propagate and promote that which they ſaw with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, ſo having loſt ſubjection to the Spirit of Truth in themſelves, which would have kept them in Unity in the Body; and having alſo loſt and laid by their ſubjection to them that were over them in the Lord, they then grew ſtubborn and wilful, and proceeded in more zeal for that which ſtood in oppoſition to the Truth, than ever they did for the Truth it ſelf; and theſe ſometimes have prevailed to the ſubverting whole houſholds, and have turned ſeveral from the Faith and ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city that is in the Goſpel, who, as well as thoſe that ſubverted them, have loſt the fellowſhip of the Saints, and the ſavour of Life either in themſelves or others; and then the Enemy perſwaded them, all are dead to the Life but themſelves; and ſo they grow to have a tickling
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135339:5"/>joy in what they do and ſay, in obedience to that perverſe and ſingular private Spirit, and ſo grow up to ſpeak evil of Dignities, and are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly, and dare to ſpeak againſt Heaven and them that dwell and inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit in it, whom God makes to ſhine as Starrs in the Firmament of his Power; but alas for them, my ſoul pitties them, when I ſee how they ſport themſelves with their own deceivings, but the day of the Lord is among his People, which hath and doth make them and their ſpirit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and their fruits alſo hath made them manifeſt.</p>
            <p>Another way that the Enemy ſeeks to break the Unity, and diſſolve the bond of Amity, is by ſowing a ſeed of jealouſie and prejudice in the hearts of ſuch in whom he can get an enterance, that ſo they may ceaſe from the true and unfeigned love, and that upon a pretended rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, becauſe of this or that, which is ſuppoſed or imagined, in the evil part in themſelves againſt others; giving heed to evil thoughts and ſurmiſes, which break forth many times in whiſperings and tale-bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; which though the thing ſuppoſed to be evil, were really ſo, Yet this is not to be allowed or given way to among you, but to uſe plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs one towards another, and ſingl-heartedneſs; and to ſhut out the evil one in this his ſubtile appearance alſo. Oh dear Friends, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how the Lord hath dealt with you, and deal you ſo one by another, he hath not ſought occaſions againſt you, but hath long born and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and exerciſed much patience and tenderneſs towards you; yet plainly reproving the evil in you, and not treaſuring it up againſt you. Oh Friends, be ye like-minded one towards another, that the Enemy of your peace and concord may be defeated, and you preſerved entire to one Head, even to Chriſt Jeſus; and ye may be one, and the Name of the Lord may be one among you; and that which tends to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king cold your Love, may be judged in all; and ſo Brotherly-Love will continue with you to the end.</p>
            <p>Another way which the Enemy works to ſcatter and to bring from this Unity, is by leading ſome who have believed, into ſome ſin and iniquity, which the Body that are in the Truth, are conſtrained to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in judgment againſt for the Truths ſake, and yet notwithſtanding the party ſo ſinning, being above the Witneſs in themſelves, which would bring them to own the judgement of the Spirit of Chriſt in his Church, they exalt themſelves above the judgment, and ſeek to gain to them, ſuch whom they can enter by their words and complaints to take part with them againſt the judgment and thoſe that paſſed it. Such were thoſe whoſe words <hi>did eat</hi> (the Apoſtle ſaid) <hi>as a Canker;</hi> of whom the Believers in thoſe dayes were to be aware: for commonly ſuch as have gone from the Power, that ſhould have kept them clean and upright,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135339:5"/>they will alſo turn againſt the power in thoſe that abide in it, eſpecially if they be drawn forth to reprove &amp; rebuke them: but let all ſuch know, that's not the way to be renewed; and let all that take part with any that work iniquity, know, that they do but defile their own ſouls there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, and do but rend themſelves from that Body, which they cannot proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per out of. And therefore, dear Friends, beware of joyning with that in your ſelves or in others, which the Power goeth againſt, let the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences be what it will; for that which doth evil, will alwayes be apteſt to ſow evil complainings of others; and ſuch as are in the unſatisfied murmurings againſt judgement paſſed upon them, are much to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for they thereby render themſelves to be the more guilty, and yet the further from repentance. But, dear Friends, watch unto that which gives you a living feeling of the living Body, which is the Church, that in all things you may demean your ſelves as true Members of it, ſerving one another in Love, and ſubmitting your ſelves one unto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the Lords ſake: That in all plainneſs and ſingleneſs, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh the Truth, you may ſeek to preſerve the Unity which the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Truth and Peace doth envy: ſo ſhall ye continue to ſtrengthen one anothers hands in every good work, and this ſhall tend to the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening of the hands of your Enemies, who ſeek to divide you, that they might rule over you. Many other deſigns doth the wicked One try, dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to break and divide, more than can now be named or here inſerted; but they are all out of the Light, and if you be in it, you will ſee them, and that will preſerve you for it's own, and did make us one, and will keep us to be of one heart and mind to the end, if we abide in it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third good effect which Truth did work in the beginning in them who did truly receive it, was <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> to God in the bearing teſtimony to what was manifeſt, though through great ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings; in which, as Friends abide in the Root, they do daily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in power, to fulfill the ſame Teſtimony: for the Mercy of the Lord doth engage them; and his anſwer of peace, in the midſt of their trials, doth arm them and encourage them, and they do hold out to the end; and for ſuch the Lord hath alwayes made a way, better than they could have made for themſelves. Yet the Enemy hath in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alſo been very buſie, &amp; hath prevailed with ſome under divers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, or rather conſultations, which he hath propounded unto them. But, oh Friends, be ye all watchful, and take heed leſt any of the teſtimonies of Truth be laid waſte; for that which leads to be weary of bearing witneſs to the Truth, and to lay it waſte, the ſame will lay thee waſte, and bring thee into ſuch a ſtate, as thou wilt want the Truth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135339:6"/>to bear witneſs for thee; and though it be hard for fleſh and blood (which hath no kingdom but here) to fall into the hands of unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able men; yet it is a more fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God; and therefore let all luke-warm-ones, who are neither hot nor cold, be now awakened, and all that have gone backwards be warned to <hi>return to their Firſt Love, elſe the Lord will come againſt them, and the day haſtens that will divide ſuch their portion among hypocrites, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they repent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to touch at ſome of the Reaſons or Arguments, which he that abode not in the Truth himſelf, uſeth to draw others into this kind of treacherous backſliding:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> He appears to ſome to perſwade them, That their former te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony was born more from an immitation of others, than from a work of the power of God in themſelves; and that now, they not finding the thing required of them, they may leave of their teſtimonies, or may do ſuch things as they have denyed formerly; this ſnare doth the Enemy make uſe of in theſe dayes. But mark who it is that he hath caught with it, none but ſuch who ſometimes were low in their minds, and dare not grieve the Spirit of God in themſelves, nor others, but for the Truth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake could give up all things rather than their Teſtimony; but in time growing careleſs, and looſe in waiting, loſt that ſubject ſtate, and grew high and exalted in their minds, above the Croſs that ſhould have cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified the betraying wiſdom; and ſo having loſt the true exerciſe of the power, and the feeling of the Excellency and worth of the Truth, they knew not the requirings of the Lord; and the earthly mind got up, that placed a greater eſteem upon earthly things, than upon things that are eternal; and ſo things that once thou offereſt up to God, thou takeſt again into thine own hand, and ſo robbeſt the Lord, and groweſt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful about outward things, as other Gentiles are; and to cover thy ſhame herein, the Enemy then tempts thee to bely the power that once wrought in thy heart, and made thee afraid to act againſt the Light, or to deny thy Teſtimony for God, in ſuch things as was manifeſt, and then ſaiſt, thou didſt it by immitation; but thou ſhalt know thy cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is too narrow in the day that haſteth upon thee.</p>
            <p>Another Temptation that the Enemy preſenteth, is, That though thou art convinced what to do, or what thou ſhouldeſt deny, yet the tryals are ſo hard and ſo many, and Perſecutors wax worſe and worſe, ſo that thou ſhalt not hold out to the end; and where he can get entrance with this bait, he preſently cauſeth an evil heart of unbelief and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ariſe, which takes away even the ſtrength which the Lord did
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:135339:6"/>give, and ſo feebleneſs doth enter the mind, and a ſpirit of bondage leads thee to fear again; and then comes the diſpute in thy heart whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou ſhalt ſtand with the power of God in the obedience, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou ſhalt fall under that power that ariſeth againſt God, and his Truth and People; and in this combate thou haſt a ſubtile Enemy, uſing many devices to betray thee; and a part in thy ſelf, not yet mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, that is ready to ſay, <hi>Pitty thy ſelf, pitty thy Wife, pitty thy Children, and pitty thy Relations;</hi> which, it may be ſometimes, are all as ſo many Inſtruments of Satan to ſeduce thee, and lead thee into darkneſs, that thou mayſt not ſee ſo great neceſſity in thy bearing up thy Teſtimony, as indeed there is, nor ſo great a danger in the contrary as indeed there is.</p>
            <p>Oh Friends, at ſuch a time as this, where is there any help but in the Lord? where canſt thou find a Saviour but in that Light which gives to diſtinguiſh of the ſeveral Voyces: Now it is good for thee to remember that <hi>If thou walk after the fleſh, thou muſt and ſhalt ſurely dye,</hi> and wither; in ſuch a time flee, flee to the Lord, wait in his dread to feel thy ſtrength but renewed at the preſent, and take no care for ſtrength next moneth, next year, or next tryal; for <hi>God is God, and chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, and will be the ſame to thee in ſeven tryals as in ſix, if thou believe and wait on him in uprightneſs;</hi> and therefore fear not man, but truſt in the Lord all ye that have known and felt his power, and let not in the Enemy of your ſouls by the door of carnal reaſoning, but keep that ſhut; and rather conſider, how the Enemy makes thee as a rejoycing among his own Children, and ſtrengthens that hope in them of their over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming all others, as well as thee; which hope is curſt, and ſhall be confounded: and conſider that if thou letteſt fall thy Teſtimony, which thou haſt once born for the Lord, thou makeſt the heart of the Righteous ſad, and makeſt their travel thorow that Teſtimony the harder for them, by reaſon of thy encouraging their Adverſaries by the hope aforeſaid. And whatever thou doſt, <hi>they muſt go thorow to the end, who will inherit the Crown of Immortality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again conſider, It may be that thy back-ſliding, or cowardly drawing away the ſhoulder, may prove a diſcouragement to others, and they may ſtumble in thy ſtumbling, and fall with thee, and never be able to riſe, and ſo thou bring their blood alſo upon thee. Oh remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber alſo, that ſervant of the Lord, who could ſay, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.157. <hi>My Perſecutors are encreaſed, but my heart doth not decline thy Teſtimonies.</hi> That was a noble Spirit becoming the Souldiers of Chriſt: yea, <hi>though perſecuted by Princes,</hi> as he ſaith, <hi>verſ.</hi> 161.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:135339:7"/>
            <p>Dear Friends, Let your minds be ſtirred up to be zealous for the Lord, in this the great day of Controverſie with darkneſs and its pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; Who hath God to bear witneſs to his Name but you? Among whom hath he made it known as among you? Who have given up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Lord as you have done? Well, <hi>Bleſſed are they that keep Covenant with the Lord, for they ſhall ſee his glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One more ſubtile ſnare of the Enemy in this matter, is in my heart to mention, that is this, <hi>Viz.</hi> To perſwade thee for once, ſomtimes to do that which the Light hath made manifeſt, with a purpoſe after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to be more faithful. Oh Friends, in the name and fear of the Lord, I exhort and warn you all to take heed of this, for this will prove but a falſe confidence, thou wilt find this kind of going out of the guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Truth, to be a dear out-going to thee; for if ever thou doſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, it will be very hardly, and with bitter anguiſh of ſoul. Oh do not tempt the Lord on this wiſe, <hi>Lest it doth prove impoſſible, upon thy ſinning willingly, to renew or reſtore thee again by repentance;</hi> thou wilt have my <hi>Pottage,</hi> but wilt <hi>loſe the Bleſſing, though thou mayeſt ſeek it with tears;</hi> for while thou <hi>wenteſt out, behold, thy way became hedged up,</hi> and the <hi>Thorny-Nature</hi> gat up in thee, and ſo thou art <hi>debarred</hi> and <hi>fenced out</hi> from enjoying thy former ſtate; Sin being entred, Death ſoon fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows. Oh remember <hi>Sampſon,</hi> who when he had diſcloſed the token of a <hi>Nazarite,</hi> in which ſtate he ſtood in Covenant with God; yet thought to have ſhaken himſelf, and to have gone forth in his ſtrength as at other times, but was miſtaken, <hi>Judg.</hi> 16.20. <hi>for the Lord was departed from him, though he knew it not.</hi> And ſo, though thou haſt known the Lords preſence and power in thy Veſſel, yet take heed of letting in that treacherous ſpirit, to lead thee to unfaithfulneſs, and to betray the leaſt of his Truſts and Teſtimonies committed to thee, though it be but for once, for thereby thou wilt render thyſelf unworthy to be found a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Power another time; for the Lord will leave that Veſſel, and often doth, and chooſeth other Veſſels to manifeſt himſelf in, that will be more true and faithful.</p>
            <p>So, Dear Friends, in true and tender Love I have laid theſe things before you, that ye might all be ſtirred up and provoked to Love and to good Works, that ye might abound in the grace committed to you; and none of you who have known the Truth, might be entangled with the Wiles of your ſubtile enemy; and that you that have begun well, might not loſe the things that ye have wrought, but might perſevere in well-doing till ye have finiſhed your courſe in peace. And Friends, this is the joy and delight of thoſe that labour among you in the Lord,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135339:7"/>and hereby is our hand ſtrengthened, and our hearts refreſhed, when we do find ye ſuch as we deſire ye ſhould be, even ſtedfaſt in the Truth; and then alſo do you find us to you-ward, ſuch as ye deſire we ſhould be, even a refreſhing in the fellowſhip of life unto you, and our God comforts us together, in the mutual joy and comfort of his holy Spirit, working in us and you.</p>
            <p>And Friends, I am the more drawn forth at this time to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit you with an Epiſtle, becauſe the Lord hath given me ſome ſight of his great and dreadful Day, and Workings in it, which is at hand, and greatly haſtens, of which I have ſomething to ſay unto you, that ye may be prepared to ſtand in his day, and may behold his wonderous Working among his Enemies, and have fellowſhip with his Power therein, and may not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed nor driven away in the tempeſt, which will be great.</p>
            <p>And as concerning thoſe ſucceeding times, the Spirit of the Lord hath ſignified that they will be times of horror and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement, to all that have, and yet do reject his Counſel; for as the dayes of his forbearance, warning and inviting, hath been long, ſo ſhall his appearance, amongſt thoſe that have withſtood him, be fierce and terrible; even ſo terrible, as who ſhall abide his coming? for the Lord will work both ſecretly and openly, and his Arm ſhall be manifeſt to his Children in both.</p>
            <p>Secretly he ſhall raiſe up a continual fretting anguiſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his Enemies, one againſt another, ſo that being vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and tormented inwardly, they ſhall ſeek to make each other miſerable, and delight therein for a little ſeaſon; and then the Prevailer muſt be prevailed over, and the digger of the Pit muſt fall therein; and the confidence that men have had one in another ſhall fail, and they will beguile and betray one another, both by counſel and ſtrength; and as they have banded themſelves to break you, whom God hath gathered, ſo ſhall they band themſelves againſt one another, to break, to ſpoil, and deſtroy one another; and thorow the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:135339:8"/>of their treacheries, all credit or belief, upon the account of their ſolemn engagement, ſhall fail; ſo that few men ſhall count themſelves, or what is theirs, ſafe in the hand of his Friend, who hath not choſen his ſafety and friendſhip in the pure Light of the unchangable Truth of God; and all the ſecret counſels of the ungodly ſhall be brought to nought, ſometimes by the means of ſome of themſelves, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by impoſſibilities lying in their way, which ſhall make their hearts fail of ever accompliſhing what they have determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and in this ſtate ſhall men fret themſelves for a ſeaſon, and ſhall not be able to ſee the hand that turns againſt them, but ſhall turn to fight againſt one thing, and another, &amp; a third thing, and ſhall ſtagger, and reele in Counſel and Judgment, as drunken men that know not where to find the way to reſt; and when they do yet ſtir themſelves up againſt the holy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and againſt the holy Covenant of Light, and them that walk in it, they ſhall but the more be confounded; for they ſhall be helped with a little help, which all the ungodly ſhall not hinder them of, to wit, the ſecret Arm of the Lord, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining their Cauſe, and raiſing up a Witneſs in the very hearts of their Adverſaries to plead their Innocency; and this ſhall make them yet the more to vex themſelves,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.</note> and to go thorow, hard-beſtead; for when they ſhall look upward to their Religion, to their Power, Policy, or Preferments, or Friendſhips, or whatſoever elſe they had truſted in, and relied upon, they ſhall have cauſe to curſe it; and when they look downwards to the Effects pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by all thoſe things, behold, then trouble, and horrour, and vexation takes hold on them, and drives them to dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and having no help but what is Earthly, and being out of the knowledge of the mighty overturning Power of the Lord God Almighty, they ſhall diſpair and wear out their dayes with anguiſh; and beſides all this, the terrible hand of the Lord is, and ſhall be openly manifeſt, againſt this ungodly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135339:8"/>Generation, by bringing grievous and terrible Judgments and Plagues upon them, tumbling down all things in which their Pride and Glory ſtood, and overturning, overturning, even the Foundations of their ſtrength; yea the Lord will lay waſt the Mountain of the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nahum</hi> 3.12, 13.</note> and the ſtrength of the fenced City ſhall fail, and when men ſhall ſay, We will take refuge in them, they ſhall become but a ſnare, and there ſhall the Sword devoure; and when they ſhall ſay, <hi>We will go into the Field, and put truſt in the Number and Courage of our Souldiers,</hi> they ſhall both be taken away; and this evil alſo will come of the Lord, and his hand will be ſtretched out ſtill, and ſhall bring Confuſion upon Confuſion, Ruine upon Ruine, and War upon War; and the hearts of men ſhall be ſtirred in them, and the Nations ſhall be as Waters, into which a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, a ſwift Whirlwind is entred, and even as Waves, ſwell up to the diſſolution one of another, and breaking one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo ſhal the ſwellings of People be: And becauſe of the hardſhip and ſorrow of thoſe dayes, many ſhall ſeek and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire Death rather than Life.</p>
            <p>Ah my heart relents and is moved within me in the ſence of theſe things, and much more than I can write or declare, which the Lord will do in the Earth, and will alſo make haſt to accompliſh among the Sons of Men, that they may know and confeſs, <hi>That the Moſt High doth Rule in the Kingdoms of Men, and pulleth down and ſetteth up according to his own will; and this ſhall men do before ſeven times paſs over them, and ſhall be content to give their glory unto him that ſits in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, Oh Friends, while all theſe things are working, and bringing to paſs, repoſe ye your ſelves in the Munition of that Rock, that all theſe ſhakings ſhall not move, even in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and feeling of the eternal power of God, keeping you ſubjectly given up to his heavenly will; and feel it daily to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135339:9"/>kill and mortifie that which remains in any of you, which is of this World; for the worldly part in any, is the chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able part, and that is up and down, full and empty, joyful and ſorrowful, as things go well or ill in the World: For as the Truth is but one, and many are made partakers of its Spirit, ſo the World is but one, and many are partakers of the ſpirit of it; and ſo many as do partake of it, ſo many will be ſtraitned and perplexed with it; but they who are ſingle to the Truth, waiting daily to feel the Life and Virtue of it in their hearts, theſe ſhall rejoyce in the middeſt of Adverſity; theſe ſhall not have their hearts moved with fear, nor toſſed with anguiſh becauſe of evil tydings, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.7, 8. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that which fixeth them remains with them: Theſe ſhall know their enterance with the Bridegroom, and ſo be kept from ſorrow, though his coming be with a noiſe; and when a midnight is come upon mans glory, yet they being ready and prepared, it will be well with them; and having a true ſence of the Power working in themſelves, they cannot but have Unity and Fellowſhip with the works of it in the Earth, and will not at all murmur againſt what is, nor wiſh nor will what is not to be; theſe will be at reſt till the Indignation paſſeth over, and theſe having no Deſign to carry on, nor no Party to promote in the Earth, cannot poſſibly be defeated nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed in their undertakings.</p>
            <p>And when you ſee Diviſions, and Parties, and Rendings in the Bowels of Nations, and Rumors and Tempeſts in the Minds of People, then take heed of being moved to this party or to that party, or giving your ſtrength to this or that, or counſelling this way or that way; but ſtand ſingle to the Truth of God, in which neither War, Rent nor Diviſion is; and take heed of that part in any of you, which truſts and relies upon any ſort of the Men of this World, in the day of their Proſperity; for the ſame part will bring you to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with them in the time of their Adverſity, which will not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:135339:9"/>be long after; for ſtability in that ground there will be none, but when they ſhall ſay, <hi>Come joyne with us in this or that,</hi> remember you are joyned to the Lord by his pure Spirit, to walk with him in Peace and in Righteouſneſs, and you feeling this, this gathers out of all Buſlings, and Noiſes, and Parties, and Tumults; and leads you to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt the Standard of Truth and Righteouſneſs, in an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Converſation, to ſee who will flow unto that; and this ſhall be a refuge for many of the weary, toſſed and afflicted ones, in thoſe dayes, and a Shelter for many whoſe day is not yet over.</p>
            <p>So, Dearly beloved Friends and Brethren, who have believed and known the bleſſed appearance of the Truth, let not your hearts be troubled at none of theſe things; oh let not the things that are at preſent, nor things that are yet to come, move you from ſtedfaſtneſs, but rather double your Diligence, Zeal and Faithfulneſs to the Cauſe of God: for they that know the Work wrought in themſelves, they ſhall reſt in the day of trouble, <hi>Yea, though the Fig-tree fail,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hab. 3.16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>and the Vine brings not forth, and the labour of the Olive-tree ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and the Fields yeeld no meat; and Sheep be cut off from the Fold, and there be no Bullock in the Stall; Yet then mayeſt thou rejoyce in the Lord, and ſing praiſes to the God of thy Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how near theſe dayes are to this poor Nation, few knows; and therefore the Cry of the Lord is very loud unto its Inhabitants, through his Servants and Meſſengers, that they would prize their time while they have it, leſt they be overturned, waſted and laid deſolate before they are aware; and before deſtruction come upon them, and there be no remedy, as it hath already done upon many.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:135339:10"/>
            <p>Oh <hi>LONDON, LONDON,</hi> that thou and thy Rulers would have conſidered, hearkened and heard, in the Day of thy Warnings and Invitations, and not have perſiſted in thy Rebellion, till the Lord was moved againſt thee, to cut off the Thouſands, and Multitudes from thy Streets, and the preſſing and throngings of People from thy Gates, and then to deſtroy and ruine thy Streets alſo, and lay deſolate thy Gates, when thou thoughteſt to have repleniſhed them again.</p>
            <p>And, Oh ſaith my Soul, that thy Inhabitants would yet be warned and perſwaded to Repent and Turn to the Lord, by putting away every one the evil that is in their hearts, againſt the Truth in your ſelves, and againſt thoſe that walk in it; before a greater Deſolation and Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on overtake you.</p>
            <p>Oh what ſhall I ſay to prevail with <hi>London,</hi> and with its Inhabitants! The Lord hath Called aloud, he hath Roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of <hi>Zion</hi> unto them, but many of them have not hearkened at all, nor conſidered at all.</p>
            <p>Well, Oh my Friends, (and thou, oh my Soul) return to your reſt, dwell in the Pavillion of the Houſe of your God, and my God, and ſhelter your ſelves under the ſhadow of his Wings, where ye ſhall be Witneſſes of his Doings, and ſee his <hi>STRANGE ACT</hi> brought to paſs, and ſhall not be hurt therewith, nor diſmayed.</p>
            <p>Oh my Friends, in the Bowels of dear and tender Love have I ſignified theſe things unto you, that ye might ſtand Armed with the whole Armour of God, Cloathed in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:135339:10"/>and your Feet ſhod with the Preparation of the Goſpel of Peace: and freely given up in all things, to the diſpoſing of the Lord, who will deliver us, not by Might, nor by Sword, nor Spear, but by his own eternal inviſible Arm, will he yet ſave us and deliver us, and get himſelf a Name by preſerving of us; and we ſhall yet live to praiſe him, who is worthy of Glory, of Honour and Renown, from the riſing of the Sun, to the ſetting of the ſame, now and for ever, <hi>Amen, Amen,</hi> ſaith my ſoul.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults eſcaped the Preſs.</head>
            <p>In page 3. line 15. for <hi>obtained,</hi> read <hi>be attained.</hi> Page 9. line 24. for <hi>preſerve you for it's own,</hi> read <hi>preſerve you: for it's one.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
